I normally teach courses on
في العادة أُدرّس مواد متعلقة
how to rebuild states after war.
بإعادة الإعمار للدول بعد الحرب.
But today I've got a personal story to share with you.
لكن اليوم لديّ قصة شخصية لأشارككم بها.
This is a picture of my family,
هذه الصورة لأسرتي،
my four siblings -- my mom and I -- taken in 1977.
أخواني الأربعة، أمي وأنا، مأخوذة عام 1977.
And we're actually Cambodians.
ونحن في الحقيقة كمبوديين.
And this picture is taken in Vietnam.
وهذه الصورة مأخوذة في فيتنام.
So how did a Cambodian family end up in Vietnam in 1977?
اذا كيف وصلت أسرة كمبودية الى فيتنام عام 1977؟
Well to explain that, I've got a short video clip
حسناً لشرح ذلك، لدي فيديو قصير
to explain the Khmer Rouge regime
لتوضيح حكم دولة الخمير الحمر
during 1975 and 1979.
في الفترة من 1975 الى 1979.
Video: April 17th, 1975.
فيديو: 17 ابريل 1975.
The communist Khmer Rouge
حزب الخمير الحمر الشيوعي
enters Phnom Penh to liberate their people
دخل بنوم بنه لتحرير أنصاره
from the encroaching conflict in Vietnam,
من زحف الصراع في فيتنام،
and American bombing campaigns.
وحملات القصف الأمريكية.
Led by peasant-born Pol Pot,
التي قادها الفلاح ألمّولِد بول بوت،
the Khmer Rouge evacuates people to the countryside
أخلى الخمير الحمر الناس الى الريف
in order to create a rural communist utopia,
من أجل بناء مدينة فاضلة شيوعية في الريف،
much like Mao Tse-tung's Cultural Revolution in China.
أشبه بثورة ماوتسي سونغ الثقافية في الصين.
The Khmer Rouge closes the doors to the outside world.
أغلق الخمير الحمر الأبواب من العالم الخارجي.
But after four years the grim truth seeps out.
لكن بعد أربعة سنوات تسربت الحقيقة القاتمة.
In a country of only seven million people,
في بلد عدد سكانها فقط سبعة ملايين نسمة،
one and a half million were murdered by their own leaders,
قُتل مليون ونصف المليون من قبل قادتهم ،
their bodies piled in the mass graves of the killing fields.
وتكدست الجثث في مقابر جماعية وميادين القتل.
Sophal Ear: So, notwithstanding the 1970s narration,
سوفال آير: وهكذا، على الرغم من السرد السبعينياتي،
on April 17th 1975
في 17 إبريل 1975
we lived in Phnom Penh.
عشنا في بنوم بنه.
And my parents were told by the Khmer Rouge
وتم إخبار والديّ من قبل الخمير الحمر
to evacuate the city because of impending American bombing for three days.
بإخلاء المدينة بسبب القصف الأمريكي الوشيك لمدة ثلاثة أيام.
And here is a picture of the Khmer Rouge.
وهذه صورة للخمير الحمر.
They were young soldiers, typically child soldiers.
كانوا في الحقيقة عساكر يافعين. بالضبط أطفال مقاتلين.
And this is very normal now, of modern day conflict,
وهذا عادي جداً الآن، للصراع في العصر الحديث.
because they're easy to bring into wars.
لأنه كان من السهل إستدراجهم للحروب.
The reason that they gave about American bombing wasn't all that far off.
السبب الذي قدموه عن القصف الأمريكي لم يكن بعيداً كلياً.
I mean, from 1965 to 1973 there were
أعني، منذ 1965 الى 1973 كان هناك
more munitions that fell on Cambodia
الكثير من القذائف التي تسقط على كمبوديا
than in all of World War II Japan,
عن تلك في الحرب العالمية الثانية على اليابان،
including the two nuclear bombs
وضمنها القنبلتين النوويتيين
of August 1945.
في أغسطس 1945.
The Khmer Rouge didn't believe in money.
لم يكن الخمير الحمر يؤمنون بالمال.
So the equivalent of the Federal Reserve Bank
لذا فالمقابل لبنك الإحتياط المركزي
in Cambodia was bombed.
في كمبوديا تم قصفه.
But not just that, they actually banned money.
لكن ليس ذلك فقط، لقد قاموا بحظر الأموال.
I think it's the only precedent in which
أعتقد أنها السابقة الوحيدة على الإطلاق
money has ever been stopped from being used.
التي يُمنع فيها إستخدام المال.
And we know money is the root of all evil,
ونحن نعلم أن المال هو أصل كل الشرور،
but it didn't actually stop evil from happening in Cambodia, in fact.
لكن ذلك لم يمنع الشرور من الحدوث في كمبوديا، في الحقيقة.
My family was moved from Phnom Penh to Pursat province.
أنتقلت أسرتي من بنوم بنه الى محافظة بورسات.
This is a picture of what Pursat looks like.
هذه الصورة لكيف تبدو بورسات.
It's actually a very pretty area of Cambodia,
في الواقع أنها منطقة جميلة جداً في كمبوديا،
where rice growing takes place.
حيث يُزرع الأرز.
And in fact they were forced to work the fields.
و قاموا بإجبارهم على العمل في حقول الأرز.
So my father and mother ended up in
اذا فقد أنتهى الحال بأبي وأمي
a sort of concentration camp, labor camp.
بنوع ما من معسكرات الاعتقال ، ومعسكرات العمل.
And it was at that time that my mother got word
وحدث أن تلقت والدتي كلمة من
from the commune chief
رئيس البلدية
that the Vietnamese were actually asking
أن الفيتناميين يبحثون
for their citizens to go back to Vietnam.
عن مواطنيهم ليرجعوا الى فيتنام.
And she spoke some Vietnamese,
وقد تحدثت بعض الفيتنامية،
as a child having grown up with Vietnamese friends.
كطفلة نشأت مع بعض الأصدقاء الفيتناميين.
And she decided, despite the advice of her neighbors,
وقررت، رغماً عن نصح الجيران،
that she would take the chance
بأنها ستنتهز الفرصة
and claim to be Vietnamese
وتدّعي أنها فيتنامية
so that we could have a chance to survive,
بحيث تتاح لنا الفرصة للنجاة.
because at this point they're forcing everybody to work.
لأنه في تلك اللحظة يُجبر الجميع على العمل.
And they're giving about --
ويعطونهم حوالي--
in a modern-day, caloric-restriction diet, I guess --
في عصرنا هذا، نظام غذائي مقيّد السعرات الحرارية، أعتقد--
they're giving porridge, with a few grains of rice.
يقدمون لهم العصيدة، مع بعض حبيبات الأرز.
And at about this time actually
وحوالي ذلك الوقت في الواقع
my father got very sick.
مرض والدي بشدة.
And he didn't speak Vietnamese.
ولم يتحدث اللغة الفيتنامية.
So he died actually, in January 1976.
لذا فقد مات في الحقيقة، في يناير 1976.
And it made it possible, in fact,
وذلك جعل من المستحيل،
for us to take on this plan.
لنا أن نأخذ خطته.
So the Khmer Rouge took us
لذا فقد أخذنا الخمير الحمر
from a place called Pursat to Kaoh Tiev,
من مكان يسمى بورسات الى كوه تيف.
which is across from the border from Vietnam.
التي تقع بعد الحدود مع فيتنام.
And there they had a detention camp
وهناك لديهم معسكرات إحتجاز
where alleged Vietnamese would be tested, language tested.
حيث يُختبر من يزعم أنه فيتنامي، إختبار لغة.
And my mother's Vietnamese was so bad
ولغة والدتي الفيتنامية كانت سيئة للغاية
that to make our story more credible,
ومن أجل جعل قصتنا قابلة للتصديق،
she'd given all the boys and girls new Vietnamese names.
قامت بإطلاق أسماء فيتنامية على كل الأولاد والبنات.
But she'd given the boys girls' names,
لكنها أعطت الأولاد أسماء بنات،
and the girls boys' names.
وأعطت البنات أسماء أولاد.
And it wasn't until she met a Vietnamese lady
ولم تكن تعرف حتى ألتقت إمرأة فيتنامية
who told her this, and then tutored her for two days intensively,
التي أخبرتها هذا، وبعدها درستها لمدة يومين بشكل مكثف،
that she was able to go into her exam
بحيث أصبحت قادرة على العبور من الإمتحان
and -- you know, this was a moment of truth.
وتعرفون، كانت هذه لحظة الحقيقة.
If she fails, we're all headed to the gallows;
اذا فشلت، سنتوجه جميعنا الى حبل المشنقة.
if she passes, we can leave to Vietnam.
واذا نجحت، يمكننا المغادرة الى فيتنام.
And she actually, of course -- I'm here, she passes.
وقد قامت، بالطبع، أنا هنا، لقد نجحت.
And we end up in Hong Ngu on the Vietnamese side.
وأنتهى بنا الحال في هونغ نقو في الجانب الفيتنامي.
And then onwards to Chau Doc.
وبعدها قدما الى تشاو دوك.
And this is a picture of Hong Ngu, Vietnam today.
وهذه صورة لهونغ نقو، فيتنام اليوم.
A pretty idyllic place on the Mekong Delta.
مكان شاعري جدا على دلتا نهر الميكونغ.
But for us it meant freedom.
لكن بالنسبة لنا تعني الحرية.
And freedom from persecution from the Khmer Rouge.
والتحرر من إضطهاد الخمير الحمر.
Last year, the Khmer Rouge Tribunal,
العام الماضي، محكمة الخمير الحمر،
which the U.N. is helping Cambodia take on,
التي تساعد الأمم المتحدة فيها كمبوديا،
started, and I decided that as a matter of record
بدأت، وقررت كمسألة للتوثيق
I should file a Civil Complaint
يتوجب عليّ تقديم شكوى مدنية
with the Tribunal about my father's passing away.
الى المحكمة، حول وفاة والدي.
And I got word last month
وتلقيت جواب الشهر الماضي
that the complaint was officially accepted by the Khmer Rouge Tribunal.
بأن الشكوى تم قبولها رسمياً بواسطة محكمة الخمير الحمر.
And it's for me a matter of justice for history, and accountability for the future,
وبالنسبة لي الأمر مسألة عدالة للتاريخ، ومحاسبة للمستقبل.
because Cambodia remains a pretty lawless place, at times.
لأن كمبوديا تظل جميلة ، تسودها الفوضى بعض الأحيان.
Five years ago my mother and I went back to Chau Doc.
قبل خمس سنوات ذهبت أنا وأمي الى تشاو دوك.
And she was able to return to a place
وأستطاعت الرجوع الى المكان
that for her meant freedom, but also fear,
الذي عنى لها الحرية، لكن الخوف أيضاً،
because we had just come out of Cambodia.
لأننا عدنا للتو من كمبوديا.
I'm happy, actually, today, to present her.
أنا سعيد، في الحقيقة، اليوم، بتقديمها.
She's here today with us in the audience.
أنها هنا اليوم مع الحضور.
Thank you mother.
شكراً لك أمي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)